Guide to the Ari and Helene Bousbib Collection of Photographs 1879-1996 PR 384
New-York Historical Society
- Series III: Photojournalism and Documentary Photography, 1880-1996
  - Subseries: NEW YORK WORLD'S FAIR PRESS DEPT., 1939
    This subseries contains a presentation album entitled "Photographs, New York World's Fair 1939," produced by the NY World's Fair Press Department. The album contains 54 large-format celebratory images, including FDR touring the site in a car, Howard Hughes with New York City officials and luminaries, models of the site, construction of various buildings (especially the Trylon and Perisphere), opening ceremonies, media coverage and photo ops, parades in lower Manhattan, visitors at the fair, and more.
    - Photograph Album, 1939 (Box 58)
  - Subseries: BEECHER OGDEN, 1951-1956
    This subseries contains 96 photographs by Beecher Ogden (1873-1963) documenting New York City. The photos, taken between 1951-1956, include images of streets, buildings, storefronts, elevated trains, pushcarts and vendors, pedestrians, and children playing.
    The N-YHS library's American Historical Manuscripts Collection (AHMC-Ogden, Beecher) holds a letter addressed to Frederick P. Keppel, president of Carnegie Corporation of New York, outlining a project, dated February 16, 1949, to document New York City by taking 5,000 images a year. Beecher proposed the urgent need of photographs of historical and topographical points of interest in the city.
    - New York City Scenes-Architectural Details, 1951-1956 (Box 54, Folder 2)
    - New York City Scenes-Bridge and Harbor Views, 1951-1956 (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - New York City Scenes-Buildings and Skylines, 1951-1956 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - New York City Scenes-People, 1951-1956 (Box 54, Folder 5-6)
    - New York City Scenes-Pushcarts and Street Vendors, 1951-1956 (Box 54, Folder 7-9)
    - New York City Scenes-Signage, 1951-1956 (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - New York City Scenes-Storefronts, 1951-1956 (Box 54, Folder 11-12)
    - New York City Scenes-Miscellaneous Views, 1951-1956 (Box 54, Folder 13)
  - Subseries: PM NEWSPAPER, 1940-1951
    This subseries contains photographs that were taken for PM News, a daily newspaper published in New York City during the 1940s. It was financed by Chicago millionaire Marshall Field III, and was known for using many large photographs to illustrate its stories.
    This subseries is arranged chronologically.
    - PM News Photos, 1940-1951 (Box 55, Folder 1-11)
  - Subseries: PORTRAIT FILES, 1937-1951
    This subseries contains portraits of William O'Dwyer (1890–1964), an Irish-American politician and diplomat who served as the Mayor of New York City from 1946 to 1950; and Alexander Woollcott (1887-1943), an American critic for The New Yorker magazine, a member of the Algonquin Round Table, and a prominent radio personality. The photographs were taken by several different photographers, some credited and some uncredited.
    - William O'Dwyer, 1940-1951 (Box 59, Folder 1)
    - Alexander Woolcott, 1937-1943 (Box 59, Folder 2)
  - Subseries: KEN REGAN, circa 1971
    This subseries consists of photojournalist Ken Regan's (d.2012) behind-the-scenes photos from the 1970s television show "The Electric Company" produced by the Children's Television Workshop. It also contains a few oversize sports photographs, including shots of the New York Yankees.
    - Electric Company TV show, circa 1971 (Box 59, Folder 3)
    - Sports and Miscellaneous, Oversize, undated (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - Subseries: JIMMIE SCOTT, 1914-1957
    This subseries contains a scrapbook that documents the life of James L. "Jimmie" Scott (1894-1985) through the years 1914 to 1952. During this time Scott was a boxer, actor, composer, ballroom dancer, and dance teacher. He also participated in dance marathons, setting a record in 1928.
    - Scrapbook, 1914-1957 (Box 60)
  - Subseries: STEPHEN SHAMES, undated
    This subseries consists of one color transparency of Bess Myerson.
    - Portrait - Bess Myerson, undated (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Subseries: UNDERWOOD AND UNDERWOOD, 1918-1919
    This subseries consists of an album containing 97 large-format news photographs depicting a host of wide-ranging topical events during and immediately after the First World War. Each photo has a printed caption. subjects of the photographs include aviation stunts, seaplanes, dirigibles, and the world's largest flying boat. There are also photos of the U.S. Army and Navy, military vehicles, European battles, relief efforts, soldiers returning home, and President Wilson at the Peace Conference.
    - Album, 1918-1919 (Box 61)
  - Subseries: CARL VAN VECHTEN, circa 1939
    This subseries contains the work of Carl Van Vechten (1880–1964), an American writer and art photographer. Images include many scenes from the 1939 World's Fair, as well as views of the Cloisters, the New York Botanic Garden, Central Park, and general streetscapes.
    - Photographic Postcards, circa 1939 (Box 59, Folder 4-5)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 62, Folder 1-4)
  - Subseries: WHITE HOUSE OFFICIAL PHOTOGRAPHS, 1953-1986
    This subseries consists of official U.S. White House photographs taken between 1953 and 1986. They include images of U.S. Presidents Dwight D. Eisenhower, Lyndon B. Johnson, Richard Nixon, Gerald Ford, and Ronald Reagan, including with their family members and other government officials. The bulk of the photos were taken during Nixon's presidency. These include performances at the White House by the original cast of the televison show "Sesame Street" and by the band "The Turtles."
    - White House photos, 1953-1967 (Box 63, Folder 3)
    - White House photos, black and white, 1970-1973 (Box 63, Folder 4)
    - White House photos, color, 1970-1973 (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - White House photos, performances, 1970-1973 (Box 63, Folder 6)
    - White House photos, 1974-1986 (Box 63, Folder 7)
  - Subseries: WORKS PROGRESS ADMINISTRATION (WPA), 1934-1939
    This subseries contains photographs that document programs created by the WPA. The WPA, or Works Progress Administration (renamed in 1939 as the Work Projects Administration) was an American New Deal agency designed to provide jobs and income to the unemployed during the Great Depression. WPA programs included public works projects such as the construction of public buildings and roads, and also employed teachers, musicians, artists, writers, actors and directors in arts, drama, media, and literacy projects. Of note are images of worker strikes and demonstrations protesting cuts to WPA programs.
    - WPA photographs (Box 59, Folder 6-9)
  - Subseries: WORSINGER WINDOW SERVICE, 1927-1939
    This subseries contains photos by Worsinger Window Service, a firm that specialized in documenting shop windows and interiors. The firm was founded by Karl Worsinger (1893-1952), a window display designer and photographer who began his career working for Gimbel's of New York.
    Stores pictured in this subseries are Bonwit-Teller, Lord and Taylor, Stern's, Russeks, Jaeckel's, and Nat Lewis.
    - Store Window Displays (Box 59, Folder 10)
  - Subseries: WURTS BROS. ARCHITECTURAL PHOTOGRAPHERS, 1911-1912
    This subseries consists of 64 photographs of the construction of the Woolworth Building. The photos were taken by Wurts Bros. Architectural Photographers, Inc. in 1911-1912. Each photograph has a descriptive title and date printed in the lower corner.
    - Woolworth Building construction photographs, 1911-1912 (Box 59, Folder 11-15)